<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: St Thomas More | Summa minutiae]]></title>
  <link href="http://summaminutiae.github.io/blog/categories/st-thomas-more/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://summaminutiae.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-27T14:25:31-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://summaminutiae.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill White]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[John Swinnerton Phillimore]]></title>
    <link href="http://summaminutiae.github.io/blog/2014/04/15/john-swinnerton-phillimore/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-15T09:16:48-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://summaminutiae.github.io/blog/2014/04/15/john-swinnerton-phillimore</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/printable/35509">John Swinnerton Phillimore</a> was a classical scholar, poet, Catholic convert and a friend of Hilaire Belloc.  The <a href="https://archive.org/search.php?query=creator%3A%22Phillimore%2C+John+Swinnerton%2C+1873-1926%22">Internet Archive</a> has a small collection of his works.  The following quotes are from his preface to the <a href="https://archive.org/details/commentaryonseve01fishuoft">Manresa Press edition</a> of the sermons of St John Fisher on the seven Penitential Psalms:</p>

<h3>The mind of a time</h3>

<p><blockquote><p></p></p><p><p>History is everywhere, if you are on the alert for her: and every book has, beyond its intrinsic quality, a further quality as being a piece or a document of the mind of its time.  What was our countrymen&rsquo;s mind like in the fatal half-century before the apostasy?  You may learn it from descriptions by historians, if you please to take their word for it, but unless you know what books any generation of men read and took pleasure in, the mind of that time is closed to you.</p></p><p><p></p><footer><strong>J. S. Phillimore <a href="https://archive.org/stream/commentaryonseve01fishuoft#page/n14/mode/1up/search/History">https://archive.org/stream/commentaryonseve01fishuoft#page/n14/mode/1up/search/History</a></strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h3>On translating English texts into modern English</h3>

<p><blockquote><p></p></p><p><p>The modern eye cannot travel freely, picking up its clues on the page, where even the commonest word is an orthographical monster, and the stops give no clue to the articulation of the sentence.  In this respect Mayor&rsquo;s text is a monument of laborious pedantry.  Consider this phrase for example :</p></p><p><p>“Every one of them wolde execute all that perteyneth to his office quykly without fayninge or parcyalyte.”</p></p><p><p>It looks a queer enough collection of beasts to set on a modern page, and one takes some little thought to discover what “quykly” and “parcyalyte” may mean.  Show this to the railway traveller at the bookstall, and his shilling will not rise to such a bait with much eagerness.  Yet nothing is amiss with it but the disguise.  Put it in modern form:</p></p><p><p>“Every one of them would execute all that pertaineth to his office quickly without feigning or partiality.”</p></p><p><p>and nothing is left that need disconcert an ordinarily literate reader.  All that outlandishness, all that air as of some quaint half-real thing raised up on the farther side of a vast chasm of time, across which we have no equal and familiar communications, is almost wholly a matter of dressing and presenting, or, in other words, of spelling and pointing.</p></p><p><p></p><footer><strong>J. S. Phillimore <a href="https://archive.org/stream/commentaryonseve01fishuoft#page/n16/mode/1up/search/Mayor">https://archive.org/stream/commentaryonseve01fishuoft#page/n16/mode/1up/search/Mayor</a></strong></footer></blockquote></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The complete works of St Thomas More]]></title>
    <link href="http://summaminutiae.github.io/blog/2014/04/14/complete-works-thomas-more/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-14T20:23:51-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://summaminutiae.github.io/blog/2014/04/14/complete-works-thomas-more</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The writings of Thomas More were scarce in 1914 when J. S. Phillimore
wrote his preface to the
<a href="https://archive.org/details/commentaryonseve01fishuoft">Manresa Press edition</a>
of the sermons of St John Fisher on the seven Penitential Psalms:</p>

<p><blockquote><p></p></p><p><p>The young student who swallows what his hand books tell him is never allowed to suspect that More&rsquo;s English works fill 1400 pages of folio. Or suppose him to have learned this much (for the literary histories mention it), he is little the forwarder.  There is hardly a possibility of his reading them.  Since 1557 there has never been a complete reprint; and only three pieces, I think, have been reprinted at all.</p></p><p><p></p><footer><strong>J. S. Phillimore <a href="https://archive.org/stream/commentaryonseve01fishuoft#page/n11/mode/1up">https://archive.org/stream/commentaryonseve01fishuoft#page/n11/mode/1up</a></strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Yale University published the works of More in a
<a href="http://yalepress.yale.edu/yupbooks/SeriesPage.asp?Series=86">scholarly edition of 15 volumes</a>
between 1963 and 1997, but 15 volumes at about $100 per volume comes
to way too damn much for me to pay.</p>

<p>The 1557 edition (funky spelling, gothic type, crappy printing, &amp;c.)
is on the web
<a href="http://www.thomasmorestudies.org/library.html#compworks">here</a> at the
<a href="http://www.thomasmorestudies.org">Center for Thomas More Studies</a> at
the <a href="http://udallas.edu/">University of Dallas</a>.  There&rsquo;s a
transcription &amp; translation job there for a young scholar with a
steady eye and an iron butt.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
