<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Recipes | Summa minutiae]]></title>
  <link href="http://summaminutiae.github.io/blog/categories/recipes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://summaminutiae.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-03T19:20:10-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://summaminutiae.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill White]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Everyday potato soup]]></title>
    <link href="http://summaminutiae.github.io/blog/2014/05/02/everyday-potato-soup/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-02T17:04:24-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://summaminutiae.github.io/blog/2014/05/02/everyday-potato-soup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Ingredients</h3>

<p>8 potatoes, peeled and diced<br />
2 quarts water or stock of choice<br />
3 onions, sliced<br />
1 cup milk<br />
salt and pepper to taste<br />
2 tablespoons butter or oil of choice<br />
4 teaspoons chopped parsley (or chervil)<br /></p>

<h3>Steps</h3>

<ul>
<li> Put the potatoes into a soup pot.  Add the water and onions and cook over low-medium heat, covered, for about 45 minutes.</li>
<li> With a hand masher, mash the potatoes in the soup pot.  Add the milk, salt, and pepper, and mix the soup, then reheat.</li>
<li> Just before serving, add the butter and parsley.  Stir and mix well.  Serve hot during the cold weather and cold during the warm weather.  When soup is served cold, oil must be used instead of butter.</li>
</ul>


<p>This simple little recipe for potato soup has become one of our
favorites.  I chose it for lunch a few weeks ago because it looked
nice and cheap&mdash;a few potatoes, an onion, a cup of milk, and you’re
off.  It doesn’t seem promising at first glance but once everything
has cooked together, it somehow becomes a beautiful soup.  You can
adjust the amount of each ingredient depending on the state of your
pantry and the calendar distance to your next payday: the first time I
made it, I got by just fine with four potatoes and one red onion.</p>

<p>Today we were out of parsley but we have a batch of chives growing in
the window in the dining room, so that went in as garnish.  Afterwards
I sighed and said, “This stuff is unusually filling,” which made the
12-year-old laugh&mdash;apparently I’ve said that after every batch
we’ve eaten.</p>

<p>The recipe is taken from Br Victor-Antoine d’Avila-Latourrette’s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Twelve-Months-Monastery-Victor-DAvila-Latourrette/dp/0767901800"><em>Twelve Months of Monastery Soups</em></a>, which I think was a gift from one of us to the other.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
